Hello, and welcome back to another
video with ItsDrdan, and today we're
going to be going even further in how
to prepare for your Chem 3A ACS final.
Now, when it comes to preparing for the
final, the ultimate way to prepare for
any type of test is not just to go through
all the chapters and to read your notes.
Um, what a lot of students tend to do,
and it's a common pitfall, in terms of
any chemistry classes, they just review
their notes and review the slides.
And then they think like, Oh, I studied.
And the thing is, that's only really
the beginning when it comes to it.
The ultimate way to study for any exam
is by practicing problems, because
that's what your exam is going to be.
It's going to be filled with
all kinds of different problems.
that are going to be coming at you fast
pace and in a very short time frame.
So you need to be practiced.
So it's one of the things like, as
I asked all my students all the time
is when you were a kid, at some point
you've tried out some sport or maybe
got into a musical instrument, or maybe
even as an adult, you got into a hobby.
Now, when you first started that out,
you probably weren't that good at it,
and one of the things that, with time,
you kept practicing it and you improved,
whatever that might be, whether it's
being a dancer, a musician, someone
who likes sports, you kept practicing.
When it comes to your
coursework, it's the same idea.
You need to keep improving and practicing.
So that's what the next few parts of
the series are going to be all about.
We're going to be going
through practice problems.
I'm going to go through my
thought process on how to do them.
So what this next two parts are all
about is these are different clones.
Of the ACS final of looking at different
ACS tests, trying to come up with the
same language and similar question
format that you will see, because
it's going to be things from all
parts of the different of the course.
So you need to be practiced in all
the different parts of the class.
So what we're going to do is
I'm going to be showing how
to do this on my calculator.
So you're going to kind of see me kind
of turn real small, and then we're
going to go into all the different
pieces and details are really type, try
to illustrate exactly what it is that
you're going to be seeing on this test.
So let's take a look.
So with this particular version
of the exam, what we did here is
we made a practice exam that helps
try to simulate as much as possible
what the ACS test will look like.
Now keep in mind when you take
the real one, it's going to be
60 questions and 55 minutes.
So if you are practicing along with
this video, I would recommend trying
to pause at the different questions.
And go through it as much as you
possibly can on your own without
listening to as many descriptions as
that we're going to be going through.
Now, when we're doing this, uh, I
will be explaining everything, so
it will take a little bit longer.
Um, just to kind of help refresh
your brain of what exactly
is that we're looking at.
Now we will have our periodic table
and then we do have our limited
resources here, but let's take a
look at our very first question.
So with the sky, the one thing
you're going to see is it says
how many significant digits are
in the length measurement of 10.
50 centimeters.
So when we're looking at this,
what we're going to be doing is
we got to count our sig figs.
So if you can remember, whenever it
comes to significant figures is that
all non zero digits are significant.
And then any sandwiched
zeros are significant.
So we know that the first three are.
The question is, what about the last one?
Well, trailing zeros are significant
if there is a decimal place.
So being that we have that decimal
there, that means that all four of
them are going to be significant.
So that would be four.
What about our next one?
It says the density of an ether is 0.
714 grams per milliliter.
What is the mass of 10
milliliters of ether?
Now, when it comes to this particular
problem, what we need to do is
we need to kind of highlight and
reflect on what piece of information
are being given to us, right?
We have that we have 10 milliliters
of ether, and then we also have
what the density is in this problem.
Now, the first thing we always
got to do is we've got to write
down, well, what numbers by itself,
what is not a fraction, right?
And you're going to see that.
All right.
10 milliliters of ether.
is a term that's by itself.
So we're going to use now with the
other value is, well, how would we
go through trying to convert this?
Well, if you remember density
is grams over milliliters.
So we have 0.
714 grams, and that's
all equivalent to one ML.
And then we're going
to see, Hey, our units.
Cancel.
So what we're going to do is 10 times 0.
714.
So let's go take a look
at this on our calculator.
All right.
So all's we're going to do is
switching to our calculator view.
What we'll do is we'll take 10 and then
we're going to multiply that times 0.
714.
And that's going to be
show our answer of 7.
14.
So what we can see is, Hey,
that matches our answer of C.
So that is going to be our
answer in this problem.
So we'll circle C and then
we'll move to the next.
Alright, so with our next one,
we have which best describes the
size and shape of a sample of gas.
And when it comes to a gas, the
thing you gotta remember is, well,
alright, what can describe it?
Well, when it came to solids, they had a
definite shape, definite volume, right?
I can say, if I pick up my calculator,
I can say, well, it has a certain
shape, it has a calculator shape,
you can measure the volume.
Same with a liquid, you can measure the
volume, but the shape can be whatever
container that it can possibly be in.
Well, what about a gas?
Well, gases are all around you, right?
You're breathing them in right now.
They're the shape of
your room that you're in.
They could be the shape of school.
It could be shape of the outside.
They can be any shape
that they can want to be.
So when it comes to trying to figure,
figure out all of this, what we have to
do is kind of read through our choices and
figure out which one makes the most sense.
Yeah.
So the first one, it has a
definite volume and shape.
Well, okay, that's a no
because that was solids.
The volume and shape cannot be described.
Well, I feel like you could
describe it, but, eh, we'll put
a question mark next to that.
Volume and shape are both
determined by the container.
Ooh, that was what we just said, right?
So, I'm going to circle that
one for now and probably assume
that's going to be our answer.
It has definite volume, but the
shape is determined by the container.
But once again, the volume is always
going to be determined by that shape
of the container once again, so that's
most likely not going to be our answer.
So let's go with that.
Its volume is determined by the
container, but it has a definite shape.
No, it's no.
So C for sure is definitely our answer.
Let's do our next one.
Liquid xenon boils at 166 Kelvin.
What is the boiling point in Celsius?
This is one of the different formulas
that you need to know, right?
So if I take 166 minus 273, right,
because when you are trying to
figure out, um, anything in Celsius,
Celsius is always Kelvin minus
273 in order to go to Celsius.
Usually you're converting to Kelvin,
usually not that much the opposite.
So if we look at our calculator and
then what we're going to be doing is
we're going to plug our values in.
So we have 166 and then we're
going to subtract that by 273.
So we'll take that and now we have
negative 107 is going to be our
value so our answer is going to be D.
Now, when we go to our next
one, it says the elements in
group 2A are known by what name?
Okay, so this had to do with
the different groups, right?
I told you earlier that you
need to know the alkali metals,
alkaline metals, halogens.
Where are they on the periodic table?
So let's look at our periodic table
and label those for ourselves.
When it came to our periodic table,
the first thing is when you're
looking at the first column, right?
These were your alkali metals.
The second column was the alkaline
metals, so our answer in this
case is that, alkaline metals.
Then, when we had our other area of the
periodic table, we had halogens, and then
our noble gases are on the other side.
So these are all these big name
groups that we see a lot, and
then your transition metals are in
the middle of the periodic table.
These are the areas you really want to
make sure you know that you're comfortable
with labeling on the periodic table So
that way you know it so that means the
answer in this case is the alkaline So
being that that said this is going to
be D is going to be your answer So now
the next one has to do with that It says
predict the number of valence electrons
for group 2 on the periodic table, which
is what we were just looking at well the
idea is is that when you have this 2a
That actually tells you how many Roman,
how many valence electrons there are.
So what that means is one
A has one valence electron.
Two A has two valence electrons.
Three A has three valence electrons.
Four A has four.
So if we look at our periodic table
real fast, and one thing that you
are going to be seeing is notice
how on all of these, they all have
those, those a letters that are here.
Those are your, that's how many valence
electrons are in the main group elements.
So it tells you, right?
So you got to be able to
read your periodic table.
So that means a 2a has
two valence electrons.
Okay.
So two, one.
We can label all of them when it comes to
how many valence electrons they all have.
So it tells you what's the
outermost layer of electrons.
Let's mark that answer off.
The answer is going to be C, and now
we're ready to go to our next problem.
For the next problem it says, what
is the core notation for electron
configuration of an aluminum atom?
Now the thing is about core notation
is that this is the same thing as
referring to a noble gas configuration.
It's just a different word
that's commonly used as well.
So let's talk about the core electrons.
So the first thing is we have to go
to our periodic table to determine
what is electron configuration.
Now when you're at your Periodic
Table the thing is you got to remember
is how we use to actually separate
and organize our Periodic table.
If you remember the first
two columns were S last.
The last six on the right were P and
then the ones in the middle were D.
Now, when we were to label
these, right, we used our rows
to determine our, our levels.
So these were referred to
as the main quantum number.
So if you do like one, two,
three, four, um, and so forth,
you could label each of these.
Um, now when we were to label
them, we kind of read our PR table,
like a book work on our way to the
element that we're interested in.
So we want to work our way to aluminum,
which is all the way over here.
So what we're going to end up doing is
we need to try to read each section.
So, but the thing is, I was asking
just about noble configuration.
So the easy thing to remember is that,
well, when we're looking at our element,
To find the correct noble gas, we look up
and to the right of that, that molecule.
That's telling you, Hey, this is going
to be neon is going to be our noble gas.
Now how do we go past that?
Well, that represents every
electron up into that point.
So it does here at your one S one,
one S two, then it does the two P six.
So from here, what you're going
to do is we look at our row.
And we see, okay, we're at the first
level, so that's going to be 3s2, and
then we look at our next electron,
which is 3p1, okay, so that would
be our answer for this problem.
Let's select that answer.
So 3s2, uh, 3p1, that would be
A, which would be our answer.
Okay, so now it says select the
element whose Lewis symbol is correct.
So the thing is, you ought to remember,
like, what, how many valence electrons
there were for different species.
Um, one of the ones that all had
to do with trying to look at your
periodic table so you can kind of
go back and forth and see what is,
which one's in the right group number.
So for example, if I were to look
at these, a lot of them, we've been
doing a lot of aluminum lately, right?
So aluminum had three
valence electrons around it.
So it should have three
dots that you can see.
You can also see it in the electron
configuration from the problem above.
Thanks.
Right, so you count all the s,
all the p electrons in order to
figure out what the valence are.
So that means that D and C, you can
immediately toss out now, gallium
and, uh, tellurium or sorry, NTL,
when you're looking at those ones,
well, those are, you can go look at
our periodic table and take a look.
So when we're looking at element that's
gallium and also at, uh, gallium,
Both of these ones are in the same
column, so we can see them right here.
So we have thallium and we have
gallium, both of those are going to
have just three dots around them.
So when we're seeing is, are
they going to be correct?
We got to see, do they have three dots?
Bromine, which was the other one
that is on row, column seven.
So that's going to have seven
dots that are all around it.
So let's see if either one
of them has seven or three.
Let's take a look.
So gallium and thallium
both have two and four.
That's not the answer.
Bromine has seven, so that matches
the correct configuration, which
was seven valence electrons.
That is correct.
Now with the next one, what is the
chemical formula for cobalt two bromide?
Well, the thing is about this one,
what you have to remember is, well,
what does a Roman numeral tell you?
And the thing is, a lot of students
think that that means subscripts,
so they're immediately going to go
to one of these first two choices
and think that they're correct.
The thing is, it's not.
It represents the charge.
So when it says cobalt two, this
means cobalt two plus, so when we
write this out, we can see that
bromine had seven valence electrons.
That means that it needs to gain
one more to make it negative.
So it'd be cobalt 2 plus bromine minus.
We're gonna swap, drop those numbers.
We're gonna bring them both down.
And as a result, what are we gonna have?
We're gonna have cobalt Br2.
Which, what that answer
is, that is going to be C.
Alright, now the next one.
What is the molecular geometry of Ph3?
The thing about a lot of these is you
aren't given any VSEPR charts, so you
have to know the basic geometries, which
is, for all the ones that are listed
in this question, I would recommend
remembering what their general shape is.
So the thing is about it, so what you
gotta remember is how many valence
electrons can each of these species hold.
Well, phosphorus generally can, let's take
a look at what its structure looks like.
When we look at phosphorus, right,
you can see it's right under nitrogen.
That means it has five valence electrons.
So when we draw phosphorus,
it's going to have a lone pair.
And then three dots on all sides.
Now, what we're going to then do is being
that we have hydrogen, we're going to
then bond it to all the single electrons.
So we're going to make dots.
So what that means is that the
structure, how many groups does it have?
Right?
We counted the number of bonding species
and then the number of lone pairs.
So it had four groups
and then one lone pair.
Okay.
So one LP.
So which one is it?
Well let's take a look at our geometries.
So with this one you either could
choose tetrahedral, which is four
groups, zero lone pairs, bent, which
is once again four groups, two of them
are lone pairs, so they're both out.
Then you have trigonal pyramidal,
that's four groups and one lone
pair, so that's our answer.
Linear had to do with essentially
two groups on each side, trigonal
planar was three groups, so it's
not going to be either of those.
The trigonal pyramidal is our shape.
Now which of the following is
the strongest intermolecular
force between water molecules?
The thing is you have to know is, is what
are your general intermolecular forces?
One thing that is, when it comes to
water, its strongest intermolecular
force is hydrogen bonding.
That's what makes it so important.
Now the hardest thing is, is how
do you know what hydrogen bonds?
Well, you got to try to remember
the following phrase is F NO, so
remember F NO to hydrogen bonds.
So if you have fluorine, nitrogen,
or oxygen bound to a hydrogen,
that means it can hydrogen bond.
It can only be one of
these three elements.
So just remember F NO, you
won't forget hydrogen bonding.
All right.
And that one's generally
our strongest one.
The only thing that's stronger than
that in terms of intermolecular forces.
is ion dipole forces, but
that's not one of our choices.
Let's take a look at our next problem.
So with this one, which of the
following molecules is polar?
Once again, this is a tougher problem.
You have to be able to
recognize geometries quickly.
The thing is, how do you know what's
polar is, it's all about symmetry
when it comes to these problems, is
it doesn't have all the same elements
found around the central atom.
For example, if I look at like CBR4,
That means that you have bromines
on all sides of the molecule.
This one is symmetrical.
They're all the same equal
pulling, so that's a no.
You can say the same thing
for CH four CO2 as well.
Now what about F two,
which is the bottom one?
Well, F two is a diatomic.
It's gonna also have equal pulling,
so you can get rid of that one too.
The only one that doesn't
have equality is HBR three.
So that's going to be your answer.
You got to look at for the, in the
equal nature within the molecule.
Now, this one we have, once again, we
have a calculator example, so we'll
switch over to that in a second, but
we need to be able to look at all the
different pieces that we have here.
I'm sorry about that.
So it says if the pressure of 50
milliliters of oxygen gas increases
from 735 millimeters of mercury
to 925 millimeters of mercury.
Okay.
What is the final volume?
And you can assume
temperature is constant.
So what that means is we're going to use
the combined gas law, but everything other
than pressure and volume is constant.
So what that's going to come
down to is P1V1 is equal to P2V2.
Now, what we're trying to do
is we want volume by itself.
So we have to rearrange the formula.
So we have to get volume by itself.
So how do we do that?
Well, we're going to divide both sides
by P2, and then as a result it's going
to end up cancelling P2 on the right.
getting P1 all alone.
So what we'll do is we'll take 735
times that by, um, 50 milliliters,
and then we're going to divide that
by 925 millimeters of mercury, okay?
So when we do that we should get
our answer, so let's switch to
our calculator to make sure that
we plug it all in correctly.
The one math trick that you can use
in these kind of video, in this kind
of problem, is you can actually use
your fraction button, which is right
next to the x to the power, So if we
hit this button right here, that has
the two boxes on top of each other,
you're going to see that it's going
to put things into its box notation.
So if we use that, it's actually
an easy way to kind of set up
your problems to make sure you
plug everything in correctly.
So it's going to be 735 times
50 on top, so you can kind of
see how that's inputted up here.
And then we got to move our cursor
down into the new box, and then
we'll put 925 on the bottom.
So if we hit equals, okay, now it's in
a fraction, so that's not too useful.
So what we're going to do is we
can hit the second button and
then switch it to F to D, which is
putting it in our decimal notation.
So 39.
7 is one way to, is what our correct
answer will be, so we'll circle that.
The other way to do this is just
the old fashioned way, which is 735.
Times 50, and then we hit equals, and
then we divide that by 925, but I think
it's always useful to know about that,
that ability to use those boxes because
it can, it can sometimes make your math
a little easier, especially if you see,
you make a lot of calculator problems,
have a little calculator issues.
All right, so then this one says
when the reaction shown is correctly
balanced, so it's saying lithium
plus bromine is equal to LBR, so I'm
going to move that up here because
it's kind of down on the side here.
So how do we balance it?
Well, the first thing is even the odds.
You can see you have two bromines on the
left, so let's make two on the right too.
So if we put a two in front of that,
we now need to even out our lithiums.
And then our bromines are all fine, so
we're going to have 2, 1, 2, which is C.
Let's take a look at our next example.
What is the typical net ionic equation
for an acid base neutralization?
Okay, so with this one, this is a
tougher one, because you have to
go through a net ionic equation.
So, you could write out the
entire problem, but kind of doing
that can take a lot of time, and
it might go over two minutes.
Thanks.
But, so one of these things is
what's easiest to figure out is,
well, what exactly is the solid
or the liquid that's being made?
So in this case, so is
there a solid or a liquid?
Well, every time you neutralize
an acid and base, it's always
going to make water as a product.
So which one of these
has water as its product?
And the only thing that
does is the first one.
So a is gonna be your answer, but
how, how can I, let me prove that
to you so that way you can see it.
So when you have KOH and HCL,
they're gonna be reacting together.
We're gonna do inside, outside.
So the inside is gonna make
water, so H and OHV together.
And then the outside is KCL.
KCL is soluble.
All alkali metals are
soluble no matter what.
So that's gonna have aqueous,
this is gonna be liquid and
these are gonna be aqueous.
So we always keep whatever our solid or
liquid is, and then whatever ions make it.
So h plus and oh or minus
are gonna make water.
And that's how you would
do that question quickly.
So now when it comes to six 16 in
the reaction, two C plus oxygen
leads to two carbon monoxide.
How many moles of carbon are needed to
produce 66 grams of carbon monoxide?
Okay, this is a slightly longer one.
So with this, right, you gotta
go from mass to moles to moles.
So we have 66 grams of CO, and what we
need to do is we need to convert this to
moles of CO, and then to moles of carbon.
So, one mole of CO, and that's gonna
be grams of CO to cancel out those
units, so we need the molar mass.
And then we're gonna do, follow our
molecular formula, which is two moles of
CO is equivalent to two moles of carbon.
So the thing is that we need to
do is we need to look up what our
value is for, from our PIRAC table.
If you don't know off
the top of your head.
But you've been doing prior to
these problems a billion times,
so you might know carbon and
oxygen from the top of your head.
So carbon is always roughly about
12 grams per mole, and then oxygen
is always about 16 grams per mole.
So what we'll do is, let's
plug in 28, and let's see how
close we get by approximating,
versus looking back and forth.
So let's plug this into our
calculator and see how we, how we did.
So what we need to do is we need to
take 66 and then we're going to divide
that by 66 divided by 20 and then we'll
hit equals and then being that it's
times 2 divided by 2 we don't actually
have to really do anything because
we're going to get the same number.
So do we have a number that's close to 2.
35, 2.
36 and you'll see, hey,
C is right there, right?
You can approximate the molar masses.
It's not like my open math or
any of these different exercises
where you have to be exact.
It's multiple choice and you get it close.
So now with this one, what is
the molar mass of iron hydroxide?
So what we need to do is we need to
find all of our molar masses for this
one being that you might, you probably
don't know iron off the top of your head.
Let's go back to our periodic
table and take a look.
Okay.
So with this one, we got to look up all
of our values on the periodic table.
We can see iron.
is right here in the middle.
So you can see it's 55.
85.
So we got 55.
85 grams per mole.
And then we're going to add that to three
oxygens and then also three hydrogens.
So oxygen on the, on the
ACS periodic table is 16.
So you do three times 16.
00 grams per mole.
And then hydrogen is 1.
008 on the ACS periodic table.
So what we're going to do is we're
going to take all those values and
add it all up to what we have is 15.
85, then we're going to add that
plus 3 times 16 plus 3 times 1.
008.
Alright, so, oops.
So now that we have all that
input into the calculator, we're
going to get a value of 106.
87.
we're Let's see if that's close to
anything that we've had from before.
So being that we have that 106.
87 value, notice that what it
matches, it matches answer E.
So that would be our answer.
So now let's go to the next one.
So it's all about speed
when we're doing these.
So now that we have 18, it says
determine the moles of water
produced when one mole of ammonium
reacts according to the equation.
So being that it gives you the ammonium
here, we need to get that to water.
So it says, alright, one mole of ammonium
is going to be reacting to form water.
So we have four moles of NH3, and
that's equivalent to six moles of water.
So what we're going to do with our
calculator is it's simply just taking
one times six and then dividing that
by four, and then we should get 1.
5 as our answer, and we
can see that's the answer.
Right.
So now what's the next one?
Which factors would decrease
the rate of reaction?
Ooh, this is an equilibrium
Le Chatelier's principle one.
So how, what would generally
decrease the rate of reaction?
Well, this is a very vague one, it
doesn't usually tell you, it doesn't
give you any of the information about
the actual, about the, what's happening
here, but what does increase rate?
Well, rate all had to do with the
amount of collisions per time.
So how, what makes more collisions?
What makes molecules more excited and
wanting to bounce all over the place?
Well, one thing is, is increasing
the concentration is going to
increase collisions, right?
The more mo more chemicals you add, the
more the reaction's going to happen.
Same thing if you add a catalyst,
the more of those you add, the more
the rate's going to happen too.
What about temperature?
Well, if you start making molecules really
cold and they start moving really slow
and they all start kind of shriveling up,
they're not going to react as quickly.
So what you're going to see is that
the reaction rate is going to slow.
So our answer in this case would be D.
Right?
So no, this is the theory question.
It's going to be a mix.
50 percent theory, 50 percent
actual, um, actually doing your math.
So let's take a look
at this next one here.
So which change to this
reaction system would cause the
equilibrium to shift to the right?
Okay.
So one thing about this, I'm not
sure why it got cut off is I just
noticed that NH3 is missing here.
So, and then to balance
that, we'll put two NH3.
Okay.
I don't know why it's deleted.
Alright, so what would
shift it to the right?
If we heat the system, which
is the first one, heating the
system would increase that.
So what that's going to do,
it's going to shift to the left.
So that's not it.
So it's not a, what
about adding an H three?
So once again, increasing a product,
it's going to move away from that.
Thanks.
So, adding goes away, so now
that's going to go to the left
as well, so that's not it.
Removing H2, so if we end up
trying to remove H2, once again,
the system is going to panic.
It's going to want to shift to the left
again to compensate, so that ain't it.
We add a catalyst, it
just increases both sides.
So, based on process elimination, it
should be E, but let's double check.
If we decrease heat.
And a shift to the right to compensate
because it's getting too cold.
So that means E.
Now the next one.
What is Q if 28.
6 grams of water is heated
from 22 degrees C to 78.
3 degrees C.
Specific heat is 4.
184 joules per grams per Celsius.
So with this one, right,
Q is equal to MC delta T.
So what you got to do is you got
to plug in your values, right?
We have 26.
6 grams.
We're on times that by C, which is 4.
184 joules per grams times C.
And then we're going to times that
by delta T, which if you think of
delta T, it's final minus initial.
Cool.
So your final was 78.
3, and then we need to
subtract that by 22.
So your delta t is going to be 56.
3.
Okay, so let's put that in,
and we're going to multiply
all these values together.
So we'll take 56.
3, we're going to multiply that by 4.
184, and we're going to times that by 28.
6.
And what we should get is about
6, 736, so let's write that
down, so 7, 6, 7, 3, 6, joules.
So which one is closest?
Well we can see E is in kilojoules,
which is roughly about 6.
74 kilojoules.
That would be your answer is E.
So let's go on to the next page
and do our last few together.
So for this problem it says determine
the partial pressure of nitrogen in a gas
mixture composed of one mole of nitrogen.
1.
5 moles of argon and the mixture is at 0
degrees Celsius in a 10 liter container.
You want to know what
the partial pressure is.
Oh boy.
How exactly can you go
about doing this one?
Well, this one is a little
bit of a harder problem.
It's going to take a little bit more time.
So the thing about it
is, well, it requires two
completely different formulas.
The first one is realizing,
well, what do we exactly have?
We want to know the partial pressure
of nitrogen, and the way that we can
do that is essentially if we take
the total pressure, we can multiply
it by the moles of nitrogen over the
total moles of the entire container.
Now we can, we know a lot of
these pieces of information.
We know the moles of nitrogen.
We can find the moles, uh,
the total moles, it's just 1.
0 plus 1.
5, so 2.
5 moles is N total.
But how do you find total pressure?
Well, one thing that we can use
is we can use the Ideal Gas Law.
So, if we plug all these values
that we have here into the Ideal Gas
Law, so, and we want to solve for
pressure, so if we do N, which is 2.
5 moles, so, uh, so being as PV is equal
to nRT, we do, N times our ideal gas flow
constant, which we can get from above.
From those, uh, different values, so
just to show you where that's located.
So you can see that that gas constant
is right here in your abbreviations.
So if you don't know a constant,
look in the abbreviations.
It's most likely there.
So 0.
0821 is your constant.
Let's go back to the problem.
Okay, now that we inputted that
value so it's PV is equal to nRT.
We have 0 degrees Celsius.
You can't leave it in Celsius,
so we'll convert that to Kelvin.
Kelvin.
So 273k and then we're going
to divide that by our volume.
So it's going to be 10 liters.
So, now when we do this,
we're going to have 2.
5 times 0.
0821, and then we'll times that by 273,
and then we're going to divide all of
that by 10, so your total pressure is 5.
6 atmospheres, for your total pressure.
So now what we're going to do is we're
going to plug that into our equation,
our purple equation that we had above.
So, we have our total
pressure, which is 5.
6 atmospheres.
Then we're gonna times that by our,
our pressure ratio, which is 2.
5 moles, is, uh, the bottom part
of our mole ratio, and then we had
one mole of nitrogen, so we do 5.
6 times 1 divided by 2.
5, and that will be your answer.
So you'll see it's 2.
24.
Now a problem like this
takes way more time.
Then you probably have available to you.
So this might be one to guess and move on
if you don't know what to do off the bat.
Okay.
So the next one, 3.
682 gram sample of KClO3 is
dissolved in enough water to
give 375 milliliters of solution.
What is the chlorate molarity?
Okay.
So now the thing about this is it's kind
of a little bit, it can be a trick problem
depending on what ion it's referring to.
So notes how it's talking about ions.
So the first thing we need to do
is we need to convert 3.682 grams
to molarity, or sorry to moles.
So what we're gonna do is we need to
look up the molar mass of KCO three,
convert that to moles of KCO three,
and then being that it's talking about
chlorate, we have to remember that
one mole of KCL O three is equivalent
to one mole of CO three minus.
Now, why is that more
important to realize for later?
Well, what if you were given
something that had multiple moles of
hydroxy, be off by a factor of two.
So you got to keep that in mind.
Then whatever answer we'll
have, we'll divide that by 0.
375.
So let's first find our
molar mass real quick.
So that way we can fill in this
missing piece that's right here.
Okay.
So being that we have KCL 0.
3.
We have K, which is over here.
We have CL, which is on the right.
And then we have O.
So what we need to do is
add up all those pieces.
So we have 39.
10 grams per mole.
We're going to add that plus 35.
45 grams per mole, and then add
that to 63 times 16 grams per mole.
So when we add all that up, what
we're going to get is we have 39.
1 plus 35.
45 plus 3 times 16, and what
we're going to get is 122.
55 grams per mole, so let's
plug that into our conversion.
Okay, so now that we have it
plugged in, what we're going to
682, and then we're going to divide
that by our, our answer from the
previous part, so which is our 122.
5.
So we have the number of moles.
Now the thing, what we're going
to do with this is now we need to
divide it by the volume, right?
If you remember, molarity
is moles over liter.
So we got to take that 0.
0300 moles and divide that by 0.
375 liters.
So now once we have that, hopefully
we'll get one of our answers.
So it should be 0.
08 is what this should be, so it's that
decimal place is moving over two times.
So it should be, E should
be your final answer.
Now the next one, it says what
is the molarity of a solution
prepared by diluting 1.
85 liters of 6.
5 molar to 11 liters.
Now the thing about this is the key
word is this one, it's diluting.
So what does that tell you is that you're
going to use the following formula.
Which is M1V1 is equal to M2V2.
So we have to make sure we
keep everything together.
So it says you have 1.
85 liters of 6.
5 molar.
We're going to take 6.
5 molar, times that by 1.
85 liters.
And then on the other side, we don't know
M2, but we know that we have 11 liters.
So what you're going to do is you're
going to multiply everything on the
right, and then divide it by 11 liters.
Okay, so let's kind of move that around.
So this will be our
formula, so we'll do 6.
5 times 1.
85, then we're going to divide that by 11,
and you should see that we get about 1.
09, or it being that we keep it to
two sig figs, you're going to have 1.
1, it's going to be A as your answer.
The next one, what is the
pH of a solution that is 1.
22 times 10 to the negative fourth
So once again, here's another
formula that you need to remember.
So pH is negative log of H plus.
So what we'll do is negative log of 1.
22 times 10 to the negative fourth power.
When we do that, right, we make sure we
put our negative button, which is down
here at the bottom of the calculator.
We'll hit our log button, which is up
here, right under the second function.
Now make sure it says log,
not LN, and we'll put 1.
22 times 10 to the negative fourth power.
to the fourth power.
So we'll put in a power function
that we'll do negative four.
Then we'll make sure that's in
parentheses and then we'll hit equal.
So now keep in mind, the number
should be between one and 14.
So if you get anything that's
bigger than that, that's telling
you something's really wrong.
So we get 3.
914 as our answer.
Now, is that entirely right?
Well, the way we tell our sig figs is we
look at how many are in the concentration.
That's going to be how many
decimal places you have.
So A is correct, it matches.
What is the conjugate base of NH3?
Well the thing about conjugate acids
and bases, they differ by one H.
So meaning when NH3 gets donated,
an H By its conjugate acid
conjugate base, that means the
other side needs to have one more.
Now would you just write NH4?
Well, if you have an extra proton,
you're going to be extra positive
because you're really happy to
have that extra proton available.
So NH4 is going to be your answer.
You always change the
charge by one, right?
in one direction or the other.
So with number 27, the way that
we got to treat this one is, well,
first is reading the problem.
So it says, what is a W over V
percent concentration of a solution
containing 25 grams of solute
in 400 milliliters of solution?
And the first thing you're probably
asking is like, what the hell is W?
Did we learn that?
Well, W is referring to weight.
So how much weight is there?
And it's weight of the solute.
And it's all over how much volume of
the solute, or the solution there is.
It's the same thing as mass over volume,
or m over v, which you have seen as well.
So what you've got to simply do is
you take 25 grams of your solute,
right, which is what's in the problem,
and then we're going to divide it
by the 400 milliliters of solution.
Then in order to find a percent,
you're going to times it by 100
percent, it's the part over the whole.
the same thing that we've done all along.
So we're going to take, uh, 25, then
we're going to divide that by 400, and
then we'll times that number by 100.
And what you see is we get 6.
25, which the answer in this case is B.
So let's do a nuclear chemistry problem.
So it says, which one is not balanced?
So for this type of
problem, not is the keyword.
You got to read these really carefully.
Um, when I first put this problem
together, I accidentally did it backwards.
Cause I was thinking like,
Oh, which one's balanced.
And you realize that three
of them are balanced.
So not means that one of them
is wrong for the first one.
Let's do it.
So if you add up the first
two, right, we have two 42 on
top and on bottom you have 94.
So on the left, on the right hand
side, we have 95 and then zero.
Meaning you have 95 and you're like,
Oh, I already found the answer.
The first one was right there.
It's already showing that, Hey,
one of these is not balanced.
The top is not okay.
So this, or sorry, the
bottom over here is not okay.
They both show two 42, but
they don't have the same number
to kind of prove that to you.
Let's say if I pick one of the ones
on the bottom, you'll see that I have
18 on the top, nine on the bottom.
I have nine and 18, I have 14 and seven.
14, and 7, all the
other ones are balanced.
So what that means is the
only answer is A in that case.
So if you find that one of
them is not balanced, that
would be your correct answer.
Now this one says the half
life of nickel 65 is 2.
50 days.
How much of a 100 gram
sample remains after 7.
5 days?
First thing is, is what you can do is,
being that we know how much time has
passed, we We can divide that by how many,
what our half life is, and that's going to
tell us it's going to be three half lives.
So, being that we have three half lives,
what we will do is we have 100 grams,
we'll go to the distance of one half
life, so that means every time you
divide by 2, so we'll do 100, divide
that by 2, right, so we'll get 50.
Now on the second half life, once
again, you're going to divide by 2,
divide again, divide by 2, we'll get 25.
And that means you'll divide it in
half another time in the third half
life, and you're going to get 12.
5 grams is what your final
answer will be, so OBD.
Now for the next one is, which is
the limiting reactant for 3 grams
of calcium is reacted with 8 grams
of water to produce hydrogen gas?
So a limiting reactant problem
means that you're starting
with two different species.
So we have 3 grams of calcium.
And then we have 8 grams of water.
So really the trick is here is you
need to get it to moles of hydrogen.
And then we are going to compare
which one made less, that will
be your limiting reactant.
So the first thing we need to do is,
well we know what the molar mass of
water is, we've done that 4, 000 times.
Water has 18 grams per mole.
So what we can do is we can simply
kind of convert this for ourselves.
So 18 grams of water is one
mole of H2O, and then we'll
convert that to moles of H2.
Okay.
So one mole of H2 is equivalent
to two moles of water.
So what that's going to tell you
is if you take eight divided by
18, and we're going to divide that
by two, you're going to get 0.
222 moles of H2 that's going to be made.
Alright, so that's one answer.
Now what about calcium?
Well, personally, I don't know the molar
mass of calcium off the top of my head.
So let's look at what it
is on your periodic table.
So, when we're at the periodic
table, you'll see that calcium
is right over here, so it's 40.
08 grams per mole.
Let's go back to our problem.
So we'll write that in, so we have 40.
08 grams, that's equivalent to one
mole of calcium, And now what we're
going to do is we'll have one mole
of calcium makes one mole of H2.
So what, all we gotta do
is do 3 divided by 40, 0.
8, 0.
8, sorry, and then what you have is 0.
074 moles of H2, so the question
is which one made a lot less, and
you're gonna see calcium made less.
So, reading the problem says
which is the limiting reactant,
it's going to be calcium.
Now the other thing to keep in mind
is for this problem, you can actually
eliminate most of the, most of the things.
The first thing is, well, it can't
be a product, so that means it's
not going to be H2, and it's not
going to be calcium hydroxide.
So you can get to the fact that it's going
to be probably C or D, because there's
always enough information in the problem.
I don't think I've ever seen on any
of these tests it not be that answer.
So it's either C or D, so if you had
to come down to a guessing game, coin
flip is better than a 20 percent guess.
So if you didn't know, but if it depends
on how much time you have for this last
problem, linear agent takes a while.
So if it's something that you only
have five minutes left, and let's say
you had 10 problems remaining, I would
say yes, and move on to the next one
would be my would be my suggestion.
All right.
So this has been my review video
of trying to go through a sample
sampling of what the ACS test would be.
Obviously if we went through this really
fast, it would probably be, you know,
take 25 or 30 minutes, but we explained
every single step along the way.
I hope that this video did help
you with, along with the series.
I believe, uh, my plan is to try to,
is to make a part 4 soon, hopefully
before, you know, your final for this
semester, but if not And this video
might be the last one in terms of
reviews and going through everything.
So practice as many problems as you can.
This, a lot of these were hand
chosen based on the ones that are
currently on the test so that way
you're familiar with all those
concepts to study hard, go through it.
You can go through this on
your own if you'd like to and
try to practice on your own.
Um, I did, I can give that to
you so that way you have it.
And I thank you so much for watching.
And if this was your first time
here and you're another student,
another class, I would love Please
consider liking and subscribing to
the channel help continue to grow.
All right, y'all.
I hope you have a wonderful
day and I'll see y'all later.
Bye now.